Guide to the Wesleyan Centennial Records, 1931
Wesleyan Centennial Records, 1931
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
1000-194
1.5
1, and 1 oversize volume
During early October 1931, Wesleyan University celebrated its centennial. The event brought together current students, faculty, alumni, parents, and honored guests including the Canadian Prime Minister. The events also consisted of banquets, concerts, recitals, lectures, and sporting events.
The Wesleyan Centennial Records features a scrapbook with badges, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, menus, playbills, and other materials. Other materials in the collection include large photographs and correspondence, including telegrams and typed letters regarding the centennial events.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Given to the library following the Wesleyan Centennial by Professor Karl S. Van Dyke, executive secretary of the Centennial Committee.
Historical Note
During early October 1931, Wesleyan University celebrated its centennial. The event brought together current students, faculty, alumni, parents, and honored guests including the Canadian Prime Minister, Richard Bedford Bennett. The events included a musical comedy, entitled The Girl and the Graduate, written by alumnus William B. Davis and originally performed in 1908. The events also consisted of banquets, concerts, recitals, lectures, and sporting events. For example, Wesleyan’s football team squared off against Columbia University, falling 0-37. The events of the centennial produced varied ephemera, including badges for alumni and event staff, pamphlets, schedules, menus and souvenirs. The event also produced many photographs and coverage in newspapers such as the Hartford Courant and campus publications such as The Wesleyan University Alumnus and The Wesleyan Argus.
Collection Overview
This collection consists of a large scrapbook and a box with file folders. The scrap book includes over 200 pages of items relating to Wesleyan’s centennial, including badges, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, menus, playbills, and more. The scrapbook is organized into categories, including sections entirely of newspaper clippings and one page with attached alumni and event worker badges, for example. The file folders contain large photographs, as well as copies of similar paper items to those contained in the scrapbook. They also contain correspondence, including telegrams and typed letters regarding the events.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Sports.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Alumni and alumnae.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Anniversaries, etc.; Scrapbooks.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Scrapbook of Wesleyan University Centennial Celebration, October 10, 11, 12, 1931
  Pages not listed below are blank.
  - Hartford Courant front page, 27 September 1931 (Page 1)
  - Reprinted front page from The American Sentinel newspaper from 19 September 1830 (Page 3)
  - Invitations to invited guests, schedules of events, circulars, etc. (Page 15-26)
  - Time Table Schedules (for transportation) (Page 27)
  - Discount certificate for guest transportation (Page 28)
  - Registration information (Page 31)
  - Schedule and menu for Alumni Dinner (Page 32)
  - Playbill for The Girl and the Graduate (Page 33)
  - Sermon, Faith of Our Fathers, by Bishop Herbert Welch, 11 October 1931 (Page 34)
  - Church Service Program, Wesleyan Memorial Chapel, 11 October 1931 (Page 35)
  - Invitation to buffet supper (Page 36)
  - Information on concerts and recitals, song lyrics (Page 37-39)
  - Information on centennial exercises and luncheon (Page 41, 43, 45)
  - Badges and ribbons (Page 49)
  - Admission tickets for events (Page 51)
  - Meal tickets (Page 53)
  - List of names (Page 57)
  - Alumnae on campus during centennial celebration (Page 59)
  - Centennial song lyrics (several songs) (Page 61, 63, 65, 67, 69, 71)
  - Wesleyan University Calendar, October 4-9, 1931 (Page 73)
  - Wesleyan Celebrates Its Centennial, 1831-1931, by Arthur H. Parsons, Jr. from The Delta Sigma Nu, December 1931 (Page 74-75)
  - A Century of Wesleyan, from The University Club News of Boston, circa 1931 (Page 77)
  - Ad for Wesleyan centennial plates (Page 79)
  - Connecticut Schools Monthly, November 1931 (Page 81)
  - The Wesleyan University Alumnus, November 1931 (Page 83)
  - Second copy of the sermon Faith of Our Fathers (Page 95)
  - Page 34 of a transcript of dinner announcements (Page 97)
  - Transcript of the centennial luncheon announcements by George Davison (pages 35-36), 12 October 1931 (Page 101)
  - Lyrics of university songs (Page 125)
  - Photos of ceremonies (Page 182-187)
  - Photos: Denison Terrace During Centennial Excercises (Page 188-189)
  - Photo: Picture of Alumni Athletic Building During Alumni Dinner (Page 190)
  - Photo: Prof. Nicolson, Prime Minister Bennett and Pres. McConaughy (Page 191)
  - Photo: Pres. Ferry, Prof. Nicholson, and Gov. Whitman (Page 192)
  - Photo: Taken at the dedication of the '92 and '93 flagpoles (Page 193)
  - Photo: academic procession (Page 196)
  - Photo: a large banquet (Page 197)
  - U.S. Weather Bureau forecast (Page 205)
  - Page from Hartford Times about the centennial, dated 9 October 1931, used in Olla Podrida (Page 206)
  - Loose item: Newspaper clipping photo of ceremony (Page 207)
  - Wesleyan Argus centennial edition, 25 May 1931 (Page 207)
  - Newspaper clippings (Page 208-243)
- Additional materials
  - Invitations, pamphlets and ephemera (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wesleyan publications and newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Planning documents (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Items relating to travel and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera--pamphlets, badges, etc. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Schedules and calendars (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Programs from concerts, recitals, The Girl and the Graduate (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Centennial events programs (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Official Football Program, Wesleyan vs. Columbia (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photos (Box 1, Folder 10)